Finding Aid for Institute of Gerontology (University of Michigan) records 1948-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Publications
  - Staff papers V, authors: Silverman; Steinicke; Tibbitts; Van Coevering; Vasey; Vinyard; miscellaneous group (Box 20)
  - Street and highway environments and the older driver, by L.A. Pastalan (Box 20)
  - A study of maltreatment of the elderly and other vulnerable adults, by R.L. Douglas, T. Hickey, and Catherine Noel 1980 (Box 20)
  - A therapeutic milieu for geriatric patients, by D.H. Coons, L.E. Gottesman, and Wilma Donohue 1969 (Box 20)
  - 30 years of gerontological research..., Symposium November 11, 1981 Toronto, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Training practitioners in applied fields of social gerontology, by D.G. Steinicke and P. Sahara 1973 (Box 20)
  - The well-being report-a look at supportive services for the elderly, by J.L. Barney 1975 (Box 20)
  - Writing about the elderly: Facts, sources, and background material for the journalist, by J. Brown, S. Haas, and J. Stevens, [1978] (Box 20)
- Photographs
  The most noteworthy items in the Photographs series are several candid shots of Susan Sontag taken at the 26th Annual Conference on Aging (1973). This small group of photographs also includes pictures of Sippie Wallace and Arthur H. Flemming.
  - Susan Sontag, from 26th Annual Conference 1973 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Photos (Box 20)
- Multimedia Kits
  The Multi Media Kits series consists of teaching and training aids developed and used by the institute staff.
  - "The staff meetings" (Box 21)
  - "Breakdown: A teaching/learning technique designed for working with the elderly" (Box 21)
  - "Nursing home advocacy: Issues" (Box 21)
  - "Age-related vision and hearing changes: An empathic approach" (Box 22)
  - "Sheltered employment for the elderly" (Box 22)
  - "The older woman: Issues" (Box 22)
  - "Challenging listening situations for older persons" (Box 22)
  - "Taking a chance on the later years" (Box 22)
  - Simulation Game (Box 22)
- Sound Recordings, 1972, circa 1950-1988
  The Sound Recording Series, primarily audio cassettes, is comprised of four subseries: 25th Annual Conference; three radio programs produced IoG; "The Aging of Europe," "New Goals for Aging" and a lecture series "Learning for Longer Living"; Miscellaneous tapes; and a collection IoG speeches, training tapes and conference proceedings. The originals of the radio programs were identified by a numerical designation preceded by "GE", although some of the tapes here are cassette copies. Few of the tapes are dated but the "GE" sequence seems to span the mid-1950s to the mid-1960s.
  - 25th Annual Conference September 1972
    The 25th Annual Conference subseries consists of recordings of the papers presented and forum discussions at the 25th Annual Conference in 1972. Most of the papers were published by IoG and may be consulted at the institute's library. The tapes here are the edited versions of the original presentations, and most are on audio cassettes. The next three subseries are radio programs produced by IoG. The originals were identified by a numerical designation preceded by "GE", although some of the tapes here are cassette copies. Few of the tapes are dated but the "GE" sequence seems to span the mid-1950s to the mid-1960s.
    - Tape 1., 7" Reel, 7-1/2 i.p.s. (Box 11)
      - Side 1. Michel Philibert, "Philosophies of Aging Around the World," 9/11/1972 a.m. (Box 11)
      - Side 2. Tarek M. Schuman, "The United Nations and Aging," n.d (Box 11)
    - Tape 2., Cassette
      - Side 1. Bernard L. Strehler, "Biological Considerations," 9/11/1972 a.m (Box 11)
      - Side 2. Barbara E. Shenfield, "Advocacy for Older People," 9/11/1972 a.m (Box 11)
    - Tape 3., Cassette
      - Side 1 & 2. Philip M. Houser, "Demographic Considerations," 9/11/1972 p.m. (Box 11)
    - Tape 4., Cassette
      - Side 1. Lisle C. Carter, "Minorities and Social Change," 9/11/1972 p.m (Box 11)
      - Side 2. Max Kaplin, "The Leisure Society," 9/11/1972 p.m (Box 11)
    - Tape 5., Cassette
      - Side 1. Leon H. Keyserling, "The Post Industrial Economy," 9/12/1972 a.m (Box 11)
      - Side 2. James Schulz, "Social Security Reform," 9/12/1972 a.m (Box 11)
    - Tape 6., Cassette
      - Side 1. John B. Martin, John D. Twiname, Bertha Adkins, "Forum," 9/11/1972 a.m (Box 11)
      - Side 2. Wilma Donahue, "Gerontology in Michigan," 9/12/1972 p.m (Box 11)
    - Tape 7., Cassette
      - Side 1. Simon Bergman, "Environment: Israeli Experience," 9/12/1972 p.m (Box 11)
      - Side 2. Nelson N. Foote, "Environment: American Experience," 9/12/1972 p.m (Box 11)
    - Tape 8., Cassette
      - Side 1. James M. Lyday, "Forum: White House Conference," 9/13/1972 (Box 11)
      - Side 2. William Oriol, John A. Love, "Forum: Capitol Hill and the State House," 9/13/1972 (Box 11)
    - Tape 9., Cassette
      - Side 1. Arthur S. Flemming," Forum: Federal Policy," 9/12/1972
        - Side 2. Wilbur J. Cohen, "Forum: The Next 25 Years," 9/13/1972 (Box 11)
    - Master Tapes: Smolic, Krkovic, Chauvet 9/11/1972 a.m., 7" Reel; 7-1/2 i.p.s.
  - The Aging in Europe, 7" Reels, 7-1/2 i.p.s.
    The first program in the numerical sequence is "The Aging in Europe." Wilma Donahue toured eight nations and interviewed gerontologists, policy-makers, and elderly people. Some of the older people she spoke with were celebrities such as conductors and actresses, and some were "ordinary" people
    - GE 1 & 2: Survey Introduction; England (Box 11)
    - GE 3 & 4: England (Box 11)
    - GE 5 & 6: Switzerland; Sweden (Box 11)
    - GE 9 & 10: Holland; Denmark (Box 11)
    - GE 13 & 14: Italy; France (Box 11)
    - GE 17: England (Box 11)
  - New Goals for Aging, cassettes
    "New Goals for Aging" is the next program represented. The format of "New Goals" is a roundtable discussion with various experts on topics concerning the middle-aged and the elderly.
    - Tape 1
      - Program 1: New Goals for Middle Age (GE 18) (Box 11)
      - Program 2: Preparation for Retirement (GE 19) (Box 11)
    - Tape 2
      - Program 3: When We are Old (GE 20) (Box 11)
      - Program 4: Financing Later Maturity (GE 21) (Box 11)
    - Tape 3
      - Program 5: Employment Opportunities for Old People (GE 22) (Box 11)
      - Program 7: Should Older People Retire to a small Farm? (GE24) (Box 11)
    - Tape 4
      - Program 6: Job Opportunities for Women over Forty (GE 23) (Box 11)
      - Program 8: Keeping Older Workers Employable (GE 25) (Box 11)
    - Tape 5
      - Program 9: Ways Communities Help Older People I (GE 26) (Box 11)
      - Program 10: Ways Communities Help Older People II (GE 26) (Box 11)
    - Tape 6
      - Program 11: Ways Communities Help Older People III (GE 28) (Box 11)
      - Program 12: Middle Years and New Horizons (GE 29?) (Box 11)
  - Learning for Longer Living (lecture series), 7" Reels, 7-1/2 i.p.s.
    The final radio program is "Learning for Longer Living," lectures delivered by noted physicians, psychologists, and pathologists.
    - GE 30: Clark Tibbitts and Charles Kidd, "Our Aging Population" (Box 11)
    - GE 31 & 31b: Karl Weller, "Why Does Every Living Thing Age?" (Box 11)
    - GE 32: Wilma Donahue, "Psychological Aspects of Aging," February 28, 1966 (Box 11)
    - GE 33: Martin Gumpert, "Physical Health Care in the Later Years" (Box 11)
    - GE 34: Moses Frolich, "Maintaining Mental Health Through the Years" (Box 11)
    - GE 35: Ollie Randall, "Family Life, Living Arrangements, and Housing for Older People" (Box 11)
    - GE 36a & b: Lionel Couzin, "Practical Health in Illness for Older People," I & II (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous
    The Miscellaneous tapes include two talks identified only by subject, and one is of an IoG faculty or administrators meeting from the early 1970s.
    - R. Lampman, "Recent Developments in Income Maintenance", Cassette
      - ? Bell, "Social Security Financing", Cassette (Box 11)
    - Ways of Mankind, "Home Sweet Home, a Study in Family", 7" Reel; 7-1/2 i.p.s (Box 11)
      (Walter Goldschmidt, producer; National Association of Broadcasters, UCLA)
  - Institute of Gerontology collection of speeches, conferences, training sessions, 100 audiocassettes approximate
    - Institute of Gerontology collection of speeches, conferences, training sessions (Box 23)
    - Institute of Gerontology collection of speeches, conferences, training sessions (Box 24)
      (continued)
- Films; Slides
  - "Loneliness and the Aging", TV spot (Box 25)
  - "Where the old folks stay" (Box 25)
  - "The prime of life", session I (Box 25)
  - "The many lives of JQP", session IV (Box 25)
  - Slides of IOG staff members 1979, 1981 (Box 25)
- Institute Files 1982-1990
  The Institute Files series is comprised of documents which are essentially internal in nature. Among the most valuable files are those in the Annual Reports folders, which offer very detailed information on the activities of staff members for the academic years 1982/83-1984/5 and 1987/88. Also of interest are the files in the Professional Studies in Aging subseries. These cover the end of the certificate program in gerontology that the IoG had offered up to 1983. They include correspondence from students and faculty concerning the change in the IoG's focus. The shift in the institute's philosophy reflected by this change was difficult for many staff members, but ultimately created an institute better able to enter the nationwide debate on geriatric issues.
  - Annual Reports
    - Personal Progress Reports
      - 1982-1985, 3 folders (Box 26)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 26)
    - Staff Activity Reports 1982-1983 (Box 26)
    - Staff Evaluations 1985
      [1 folder CLOSED; removed to vault]
    - Staff Research Needs 1984 (Box 26)
  - Animal Care--North Ingalls Building 1984 (Box 26)
  - Application for Long-Range Support undated, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Associations and Organizations
    - Aging Society Policy Studies Center 1987-1988 (Box 26)
    - Association for Gerontology in Higher Education 1987 (Box 26)
    - International Center for Social Gerontology
      - Correspondence and Memos 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - International Course in Social Gerontology 1970 (Box 26)
    - Michigan Coalition of Aging Organizations
      - Agendas and Notes 1989-1990 (Box 26)
      - Correspondence 1989-1990 (Box 26)
    - Michigan Office of Service to the Aging
      - History of the Medicare Problem 1987 (Box 26)
      - News Service Reports 1987-1989 (Box 26)
    - National Center on Black Aged 1979-1980 (Box 26)
    - Turner Advisory Council Agendas and Minutes 1989-1990 (Box 26)
  - Biomedical Research Council 1982-1983 (Box 26)
  - Budget 1984/85-1985/86 (Box 26)
  - Continuing Education Program
    - Correspondence and Memos 1982-1985, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Workshops 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Corporate/Commercial Research Affiliations
    - Carnegie Corporation 1987 (Box 26)
    - Presidential Foundation 1989 (Box 26)
    - The Travelers Retirement Job Bank 1988 (Box 26)
  - Development Project Proposals
    - Aging Media Information Center 1984 (Box 26)
    - Continuing Education in Aging 1983-1984 (Box 26)
    - Correspondence 1982-1984 (Box 26)
    - Seasons of Life 1984 (Box 26)
  - Eastern Michigan University 1983-1985 (Box 26)
  - Geriatric Education Center
    - General 1983-1984 (Box 26)
    - Agendas and Minutes 1983-1984 (Box 26)
    - Curriculum Task Force 1983-1984 (Box 26)
    - Memos 1984-1986 (Box 26)
    - Planning Committee 1984 (Box 26)
    - Project Proposal undated (Box 26)
    - Urinary Incontinence 1984 (Box 26)
  - IoG Division of Research
    - Correspondence 1983 (Box 26)
    - Faculty Associates 1984 (Box 26)
    - Staff Meeting Minutes 1983-1985 (Box 26)
    - Staff Memoranda 1983-1984 (Box 26)
    - Turner Program 1977-1985, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - IoG Division of Research Utilization
    - Budget for 1983/84 (Box 26)
    - Research Seminar Program 1982-1983 (Box 26)
    - Unit Proposals undated (Box 26)
  - Institute Library 1986-1987 (Box 26)
  - Kara, Gail 1987-1988 (Box 26)
  - Professional Studies in Aging (Box 27)
    - Alumni Survey 1980 (Box 27)
    - Certificate Program
      - Applications 1983-1984 (Box 27)
      - Background 1977-1986 (Box 27)
      - Correspondence, Reports and Schedules 1982-1984 (Box 27)
      - Departmental Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 27)
      - Planning Objectives 1983 (Box 27)
    - Correspondence 1985-1986 (Box 27)
    - Course Lists 1987-1989 (Box 27)
    - Statistics 1985-1986 (Box 27)
    - Support Letters 1984 (Box 27)
  - Research Advisory Committee 1982-1984 (Box 27)
  - Research Program
    - Annual Report 1988-1989 (Box 27)
    - Orientation Handbook 1989 (Box 27)
  - Retirement Planning Program Bibliographies 1981 (Box 27)
  - Shock, Nathan 1988-1989 (Box 27)
  - Site Visits
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1984-1985 (Box 27)
    - Report 1985 (Box 27)
    - Visit to IOG 1981-1982 (Box 27)
  - Staff Meetings 1983-1984 (Box 27)
  - Staff Reports and Papers
    - Donahue, Wilma
      - "The Common Body of Knowledge" undated (Box 27)
      - Office of Vocational Research Proposal 1962 (Box 27)
      - "Older Women Workers" undated (Box 27)
      - Preparing for Retirement 1952-1953 (Box 27)
      - Rehabilitation 1960 (Box 27)
      - Religion undated (Box 27)
      - Statistics undated (Box 27)
    - Gottesman, Leonard undated (Box 27)
    - Hunter, Woodrow, Preretirement Education 1960-1962 (Box 27)
    - Tibbitts, Clark 1948-1951 (Box 27)
  - Special Reports 1951-1968 (Box 27)
  - Task Force on Curriculum Planning 1983 (Box 27)
  - Visiting Scholars Program undated (Box 27)
  - Veterans Administration Hospital (VA)
    - Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center Budget 1979 (Box 27)
    - Heckler Bill 1979 (Box 27)
  - Workshops, Presentations, Symposia
    - Diabetes and the Elderly 1985 (Box 27)
    - Knowledge Utilization 1985 (Box 27)
    - National High School Debate on Aging 1988-1989 (Box 27)
    - Policy Making under Reaganomics 1986 (Box 27)
    - Research Utilization 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Unidentified Symposium 1973 (19 Photographs Only) (Box 27)
    - Wilbur Cohen Symposium 1988 (Box 27)
- University Files 1972-1988
  The University Files series is more administrative in nature, and is broken into two subseries based on the relationship between IoG and the respective UM unit. The first subseries, Academic Units, details the IoG's focus on interdisciplinary research. The IoG made alliances with a surprising variety of UM units (for example, with the School of Music, the School of Architecture and the Department of Biology) to further research and understanding of the aging process in a holistic manner. The second subseries, Administrative Units, is less illuminating; although it does illustrate some of the IoG's dealings with the university administration, it does so in a cursory and inconsistent way. The most interesting files show the close relationship between the IoG Chairman, Richard Adelman, and the man he succeeded, Harold Johnson, who left IoG to become Vice President for Academic Affairs.
  - Academic Units
    - Architecture and Urban Planning, College of
      - Correspondence 1974-1978 (Box 28)
      - Correspondence with Leon Pastalan 1982-1983 (Box 28)
    - Bio-Medical Program (Dr. Adelman) 1977 (Box 28)
    - Dentistry, School of 1976-1988 (Box 28)
    - Economics, Department of 1977 (Box 28)
    - Education, School of
      - Correspondence 1972-1981, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - External Degree Program 1979 (Box 28)
    - Extension Service 1978-1979 (Box 28)
    - Health Services Research Center 1977-1978 (Box 28)
    - Hospital
      - General 1979-1983 (Box 28)
      - Internal Medicine 1982-1986 (Box 28)
    - Human Growth and Development, Center for 1983-1984 (Box 28)
    - Institutes
      - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities 1975-1978 (Box 28)
      - Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations undated (Box 28)
      - Institute for Social Research
        - F. Thomas Juster Memoranda 1980 (Box 28)
        - General 1977-1984 (Box 28)
    - Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) 1977-1979 (Box 28)
    - Laboratory Medicine, Unit for 1982-1986 (Box 28)
    - Literature, Science & Arts, College of
      - General 1979-1987 (Box 28)
      - Biological Sciences, Division of 1979-1986 (Box 28)
      - Journalism, Department of 1976 (Box 28)
      - Political Science, Department of 1978-1980 (Box 28)
      - Psychology, Department of 1974-1977 (Box 28)
      - Sociology, Department of 1979 (Box 28)
    - Medical School
      - General 1977-1979 (Box 28)
      - Biological Chemistry, Division of 1984 (Box 28)
      - Family Practice 1978-1983 (Box 28)
    - Mental Health Research Institute 1985-1988 (Box 28)
    - Music, School of 1977 (Box 28)
    - Physical Education, Department of 1977-1979 (Box 28)
    - Public Health, School of
      - Correspondence 1973-1986, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - Epidemiology, Department of 1979 (Box 28)
      - Health Gerontology Program
        - Correspondence 1979-1983 (Box 28)
        - Reports 1978/79-1980/81 (Box 28)
    - Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1977-1981 (Box 28)
    - Social Work, School of 1977-1981 (Box 28)
    - University Library 1986 (Box 28)
  - Administrative Units
    - Academic Affairs, Vice President for
      - Correspondence 1975-1987, 3 folders (Box 28)
      - Institute and Center Directors' Meeting 1978 (Box 28)
      - Unemployment Insurance 1979 (Box 28)
    - Academic Planning and Analysis, Office of 1978-1979 (Box 28)
    - Affirmative Action
      - Correspondence 1977-1984 (Box 28)
      - Goals and Achievements 1973 (Box 28)
      - University Age Concerns Council 1982 (Box 28)
    - Financial Affairs, Vice President for 1976-1983 (Box 28)
    - General Counsel, Office of 1975-1980 (Box 28)
    - President, Office of 1977-1985 (Box 28)
    - Regents, Board of 1984-1985 (Box 28)
    - State Relations, Vice President for 1984-1987 (Box 28)
    - University Relations and Development, Vice President for 1976-1980 (Box 28)